Preliminary Guide to the Special Collections Department, Gelman Library records, 1819-2014 RG0110
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Janet G. Travell exhibit, 2003; RG0110 Series 14; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell as a student at Brearley High School, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell holding her daughters, 07/1936 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photo reproduction of young Dr. Travell rowing a boat, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Photocopy of temporalis, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell demonstrating ethyl chloride spray on a patient, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Photo copies of slides used in Dr. Travell's lecture on chest and arm pain at Menninger Foundation in Topeka, Kansas [1/3], undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Photo copies of slides used in Dr. Travell's lecture on chest and arm pain at Menninger Foundation in Topeka, Kansas [2/3], undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Photo copies of slides used in Dr. Travell's lecture on chest and arm pain at Menninger Foundation in Topeka, Kansas [3/3], undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Photocopy of "How to Give Painless Injections" abstract, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell drawing the body, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Scanned reproduction of skin, muscle, and bone graphs of the leg, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Photocopy of the contents of "The Doctor's Bag", undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Photo reproduction of skeleton sitting on chair, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Photocopy of a drawn female figure sitting on a chair, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Scanned reproduction of a man on a John Deere Tractor, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell attending the Foundation for Orthodontic Research Symposium in Palm Springs, California, 04/14/1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Photocopy Doer's Profile from Washington Times, 07/04/1996 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Photocopy of Dr. Travell riding her horse at summer home in Sheffield, Massachusetts, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell speaking at a conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Photocopy of Dr. Travell's cartoon in Today's Family Doctor, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Photocopy of the speech "The Progress of Women in Medicine" by Elise S. L'Esperance, MD, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Photocopy of letter for Woman of the Year, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Photo reproduction of JFK and Dr. Travell leaving his Georgetown home, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Photocopy of the rocking chair cartoon "I don't find this relaxing at all", undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Photocopy of the article "First Lady (MD) in the White House", undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Scanned reproduction of Dr. Travell, her daughters and husband in her White House Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Scanned reproduction of Dr. Travell posing next to a picture of JFK, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Courtesy of AP photo archives
  - Scanned reproduction of Dr. Travell and JFK in the Oval Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Photocopy of Dr. Travell and her husband seeing her daughter and grandson off to Europe, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Photocopy of Dr. Travell and her husband at a British Embassy Garden Party, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell and Mrs. Samuel M. Burgess II, President of GW Hospital Women's Board, sitting on rocking chair, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Photo Reproduction of Dean John Parks and Dr. Travell attending a meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    From Acc#41, box 10
  - Scanned reproduction of a "Prescription for Happiness.. .", undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Photo reproduction of Dr. Travell in her office, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Photocopy of Dr. Travell's curriculum vitae, 02/1964 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Photocopy reproduction of Dr. Travell and her husband, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Photocopy of Life magazine article "Presidential Chair Rocks the Country", 04/1961 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Text label "Are the Children of Women Doctors Neglected?" by Dr. Travell's daughter, Virginia, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- March on Washington exhibit, 1998; RG0110 Series 15; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This series contains programs, postcards, photographs, reproduced news clippings, mounted materials, replicas, and videocasettes. These items were produced for the exhibit and reception associated with the exhibit commemorating the 35th anniversary of the March on Washington.
  - Mounted materials, Series 15
    - Box 2, Series 15 (Flat box 2)
    - Box 3, Series 15 (Flat box 3)
    - Folder 1, Series 15 (Map-folder 1)
    - Folder 2, Series 15 (Map-folder 2)
    - Folder 3, Series 15 (Map-folder 3)
  - Photographic materials, Series 15
    - Box 4, Series 15 (Flat box 4)
    - Box 5, Series 15
  - Replicas, Series 15 (Object 1, Object 2)
    Two replica picket signs made for the March on Washington Exhibit.
- Exhibits, RG 0110 Series 16
  - Exhibit General Materials:, Series 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1935, RG 0110 Series 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1956 "Documents and Photographs From the Permanent Collection", RG 0110 Series 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Events, 13 October 2010; 2010; RG0110 Series 17; 0.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box
  This series contains material concerning events sponsored by the Special Collections Research Center. Materials include invitations and a commemorative book for opening of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Labor History Research Center, 13 October 2010; a VHS videotape of an event for the Jack Anderson papers 19 October 2007; and a VHS videotape of a Kiev event, 27 April 2006.
  - Opening of the Labor History Research Center, 13 October 2010; Series 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kiev event, VHS videotape, 27 April 2006; Series 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jack Anderson papers event, VHS videotape, 19 October 2007; Series 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- UA Records Management Program Files, Between 1985 and 2002; RG0110 Series 18; 13.75 Linear Feet 11 Bankers boxes (Box 7, Box 6, Box 5, Box 4, Box 10, Box 9, Box 8, Box 3, Box 2, Box 1, Box 11)
  General
  This series includes what looks like research undertaken by the previous UA in an attempt to develop a records management program. These boxes were found in the current university archvist's office Bergis Jules in Septemer 2012. Box 11 was found while processing series 20 in 2019. Because this material did not relate to the subject matter of series 20, it was added to series 18.
  - University Archives Records Management Program UARMP, 1978-1990 (Box 11, Folders 1-4)
- Diversity Fellowship student projects collection, 2014; Series 19; 12 digital object(s)
  Biographical / Historical
  The inaugural cohort of University Archives Diversity Research Fellows—students Eden Orelove, Isabel Garcia, Tasha Dorsey and Dominic Amaral—spent an academic year combing through the University Archives at the GW Libraries to dig up these unsung stories, examining the lives of the nonacademic staff, women, international students and veterans who have contributed to GW's history.
  The program was developed by the University Archivist to bring the campus community closer to the history of the university. This project gives students the opportunity to assist the work of the University Archives to preserve the fascinating legacy of GW.
  The fellows were selected by a committee of faculty and staff from the Special Collections Research Center at the beginning of the academic year and awarded a stipend. Funding for the program was supplied through an Innovations in Diversity and Inclusion grant from the Office of Diversity and Inclusion.
  The plan is for the diversity fellowship program to cotinue.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by Jenny Kinniff, June 13, 2014
  Conditions Governing Access
  This collection is open for research. Currently the digital files are housed on a dark server in Special Collections. See staff for access.
  best
  Organized chronologically by Fellowship cohort.
  This series contains the digital files of the Fellows. These include formats such as Powerpoint of the final presentations, Word documents of the research conducted and analysis of data, and mp3 files of interviews. These documents were all created in 2014.
  - 2014 Fellowship, Series 19 Subseries 1
    Arranged alphabeically by last name of Fellow.
    - Dominic Amaral, 2014; Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 1
      A veteran, Mr. Dominic Amaral, B.A. '14, applied for the program at the urging of Michael Ruybal, associate director of the Office of Military and Veteran Student Services. Mr. Amaral scoured 50 years of veterans' history at GW, beginning with 1900. He was fascinated by the university's flexibility at the onset of World War I, when GW developed courses focused on firearms, camouflage and ship hull engineering to better educate the changing student body. By the end of WWI there were 1,200 veterans out of 3,200 students, he said.
      - diversityproject_amaral_2014_rosters, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 1
      - diversityproject_amaral_2014_sources, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 1
      - diversityproject_amaral_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 1
      - diversitypresentation_amaral_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 1
    - Tasha Dorsey, 2014; Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 2
      Tasha Dorsey, a graduate student in the Columbian College of Arts and Sciences' clinical psychology program, based her project friendships she formed with the cafeteria staff an undergraduate at the United States Naval Academy. These relationships inspired her interest in researching the lives of staff members at GW.
      - diversityproject_dorsey_2014_Interview with Douglas Johnson, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 2
      - diversityproject_dorsey_2014_Interview with Armecia Banks, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 2
      - diversityproject_dorsey_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 2
      - diversitypresentation_dorsey_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 2
    - Isabel Garcia, 2014; Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 3
      For rising senior Isabel Maria Garcia, a native of Ecuador, the project was personal. Garcia studied the emergence of international students at GW. Garcia said that the development of the English as a Foreign Language program, founded in the 1970s to serve international students, was a turning point for the international community on campus. By the mid-1970s there were 1,229 foreign students from 101 countries attending GW.
      - diversitypresentation_garcia_2014_notes, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 3
      - diversitypresentation_garcia_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 3
    - Eden Orelove, 2014; Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 4
      Eden Orelove conducted an in-depth study of women at GW and found that the Columbian Women organization has been a champion for female students for 125 years. She said that researching the place of women at GW in history was an important experience, from discovering the stories of alumni pioneers such as Antarctic explorer Jackie Ronne and aviator Jacqueline Cochran to learning about the Columbian Women's contribution to purchase a gram of radium for scientist Marie Curie.
      - diversityproject_orelove_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 4
      - diversitypresentation_orelove_2014, Series 19 Suberies 1 Subsubseries 4
- Accession Records, 1930-2002; RG0110 Series 20; 7 Linear Feet 5 Letter Boxes, 1 Legal Box, 1 Legal Slim Box, 1 Letter Slim Box
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Series 20 contains material related to acquisitions of the special collections. This material includes finding aids, inventory lists and descriptions. The material dates between 1930 -2002. This range describes the dates that these materials were acquired, not to the date of the actual material that was aquired.
  - Acc # 3, 5-7, 9, 11, 12, 14-16, 18-19, 21-25, 27-32, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acc # 33-43, 46, 48-50, 52-56, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Acc # 57-72, 74-79, 81-84, 87-90, 93-97, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Acc # 98, 100-114, 116-118, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Acc # 119-122, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Acc # 123-24, 127-31, 135, 137, 139, 141, 143-47, 149-54, 157-59, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Acc # 161-63, 165-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Acc # 180-96, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Acc # 197-200, 206-09, 211, 213, 215, 219-21, 223-25, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Acc # 228-30, 233, 237, 243, 263, 265, 285, 302, 313-17, 319-21, 323-39, 341, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Acc # 342, 1972 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Acc # 343-44, 347, 350-51, 353-55, 357, 359-64, 367, 374, 376-386, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Acc # 387, 390-91, 393, 400, 406, 409-10, 412, 415, 418, 421-25, 427-28, 430-32, 434, 437-42, 444-55, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Acc # 456, 459-64, 466-68, 470-75, 477, 479-87, 500, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Acc # 501-05, 507-08, 511, 513, 515, 518-19, 521-23, 526-28, 531, 533, 535-40, 544, 546-48, 552, 554-61, 563-66, 568-74, 576, 578, 580-81, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Acc # 583-87, 589, 594, 596-98, 600-01, 603-04, 610, 616, 618, 620-21, 623, 626, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Acc # 627-28, 632-33, 643, 649, 651, 653-55, 659-60, 665-68, 670-72, 675, 677-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Acc # 683-85, 687, 691, 698-99, 702-03, 705-07, 709, 711-12, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Acc # 714, 717-18, 720-21, 726, 729-31, 738, 740, 743, 749-50, 755-56, 760-63, 767-68, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Acc # 775, 777, 782, 784, 789-90, 793, 802, 804, 806, 809, 812, 818-19, 821-25, 829, 832, 837-40, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Acc # 846, 848, 854-55, 857, 862, 866, 871, 877, 884, 886, 891, 895, 897-99, 903, 905-09, 911, 921, 924-26, 929-31, 934-35, 937-40, 845, 961, 963, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Acc # 971-73, 976-77, 1002, 1006-08, 1011-13, 1015, 1017-18, 1026-31, 1034, 1036, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Acc # 1038-44, 1046, 1048-49, 1051, 1054-55, 1057-58, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Acc # 1061, 1064, 1066, 1068, 1070-73, 1075-78, 2005.002, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Amitai Etzoni Papers (Acc # 657), 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Archives, undated (Box 4, Folders 4-5)
  - Archive Photos Collection Index, 1930-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trustees (Acc #0), undated (Box 4, Folders 7-8)
  - Cherry Tree Photo Collection (Acc #210) RG 113 Ser. 10, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Distinguished Alumni Achievement Awards (Acc # 236), undated (Box 5, Folders 1-2)
  - Faculty/Alumni Collections, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Finding Aids to Various Collections, undated (Box 5, Folders 4-5)
  - George W. Hoffman Collection (Acc # 126), 1992 April 02 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Guide to Related Choral Activities (Acc # 374), c. 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - GW Publications Past and Present, 2002 May (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hatchet (Acc # 280), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hatchet Photo Collection (Acc # 234), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hillel Collection (Acc # 509), 10/2002 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Honorary Degree Recipients (Acc # 368), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Index to Alumni Review (Acc # 894), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Index to GW Magazine (Acc # 417), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Index for Negative Collection (Acc # 879), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Indices for Archival and University Relations Photo Collections (Acc # 133, 299), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Marvin Ickow Negative Collection (Acc # 2), undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - News Release Collection (Acc # 308) RG 044 Ser. 13, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photo Collections, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photo Working File, c. 1970-1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - President's Archives (Acc # 289,900), 1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Presidents' Papers (Acc # 13, 289, 311, 499), undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - University Bulletin (Acc # 278), undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Vertical Files Index (Acc # 274), undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Administrative records, RG0110 Series 21
  - Archives mission statement drafts, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Donations - correspondence, 1984-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photo source material (acc 299), 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Locations of University Archives images throughout campus, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles about GW history, 1970-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legacy information from David Anderson, 1990-2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foggy Bottom walking tour, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Records management, 1988-2015 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mount Vernon campus archives, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chartered organizations histories, 1968-2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Campus plan, 2006-2025 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Transition notebook for W. Keller, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Assistant university archivist operations manual, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Records management and NHPRC grant, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Preserving GW History newsletter, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NHPRC narrative: A full archives/records management program for GWU, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Production of a records manual for campus binder (2 folders), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)